<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Docker on DazzLog</title><link>https://blog.dazzlog.de/tags/docker/</link><description>Recent content in Docker on DazzLog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>dazz - [Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 23:42:23 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.dazzlog.de/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Build your own s6-overlay base image</title><link>https://blog.dazzlog.de/posts/2024-08-19_base-image-with-s6-overlay/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 23:42:23 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.dazzlog.de/posts/2024-08-19_base-image-with-s6-overlay/</guid><description>S6-overlay is a container-focused process manager that offers end-to-end management of the container&amp;rsquo;s lifecycle, from initialization to graceful shutdown.
To make use of s6-overlay we need to add the binaries to our container by adding, extracting and then moving them to the directory where they are expected.
ADD https://github.com/just-containers/s6-overlay/releases/download/3.2.0.0/s6-overlay-noarch.tar.xz /tmp ADD https://github.com/just-containers/s6-overlay/releases/download/3.2.0.0/s6-overlay-x86_64.tar.xz /tmp Update dependencies When adding the s6-overlay sources to in a Dockerfile we want to make sure that we get notified when a new version is available, so we can always be up-to-date with all our libraries.</description></item><item><title>Environment variables in a dockerized Symfony</title><link>https://blog.dazzlog.de/posts/2023-01-02_environment-variables-in-a-dockerized-symfony/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 19:24:18 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.dazzlog.de/posts/2023-01-02_environment-variables-in-a-dockerized-symfony/</guid><description>I have developed a Symfony Web-Application, and it runs locally in a dockerized environment with docker-compose. This app is going to be deployed to production as a docker container. In production the handling of environment variables and how they are passed to the container during development is different.
12 Factor App A few points from the 12factor methodology:
III. Config: Store config in the environment since env vars are easy to change between deploys without changing any code X.</description></item><item><title>Build and push docker images to ghcr.io with GitHub Actions</title><link>https://blog.dazzlog.de/posts/2022-12-28_build-and-push-docker-images-to-ghcr-with-github-actions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 00:25:38 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.dazzlog.de/posts/2022-12-28_build-and-push-docker-images-to-ghcr-with-github-actions/</guid><description>When you host your project code on GitHub and want to release it as a docker image for deployment or just publish it, the way to go are GitHub actions. Actions are basically hooks that can start CI/DC workflows on repository events.
GitHub actions can be used to build and push images to GitHub’s Container Registry which are reachable under https://ghcr.io which is part of the package registry. The package registry is not only for docker images, it can also host quite a few other kinds of packages.</description></item></channel></rss>